1.2, the importance of project management.
The BIMBOC guide defines
project management, and
it's important to remember
this definition as well.
Project management is the application of
knowledge, skills, tools and techniques to
project activities to meet the project
requirements.
Project management is accomplished through
the appropriate application and
integration of the project management
processes.
identifying for the project.
Project management
enables organisations to
execute projects
effectively and efficiently.
Stop for a moment.
Did you notice what I just said?
Project management
enables organisations to
execute projects
effectively and efficiently.
Does that mean the projects can be
completed without project management?
Yes, that's exactly what it means.
Is that a surprise.
Many of the tools and
techniques for project
management were
developed in the last century.
For example, the Gant chart, which is the
basis of a project schedule, was developed
in 1917 by Henry Grant and used in
building ships for the First World War.
Computerised project scheduling was first
used in 1957 for the DuPont Organization
for decommissioning obsolete factories And
PDM, the precedence diagramming method,
also known as Activity on Node,
was invented in the 1960s by John Fondale,
as a hand-drawn alternative to the
Activity on Arrow method used by computers.
Ironically, modern scheduling software is
based on John Fondale's hand-drawn
precedent diagramming
method rather than the Activity
on Arrow method, which is
originally used by computers.
The Critical Path was foreshadowed in the
1950s by the US Navy in Critical Chain,
but then developed by John Fondow and
others into the Critical Path method.
John Fondale also helped to fund the
Project Management Institute in 1969,
and he later served as its president and
chairman.
Possibly the oldest project management
technique has its roots in the second half
of the 17th century when Blaise Pascal and
Pierre de Format developed probability
theory which led to
considerable improvements
in calculating premiums
for shipping insurance.
Actual risk management was probably
developed in the first half of the 20th
century and then in 1956 Russell
Gallagher introduced the term
risk management in the whole
Harvard Business Review Volume 34.
But the point I'm trying to
make is that all of the main
tools and techniques of project
management are quite recent.
Now let's think about the
building of the pyramids
and that's often stated
as one of the first projects.
Each one is a very large temporary endeavor
that was created as a unique product.
This means that by definition the creation
of each pyramid passes a test for a
project because if you remember the
pyramids were built for the death of a
pharaoh before the pharaoh was actually
dead usually and so that means it would be
working on quite a tight time scale and so
it wasn't considered an operation actually
one of the things that really surprised me
was i always thought that pyramids had
been built by teams of slaves because
that's what we learned in high school but
what was later discovered was that in
Egypt they had a type of national service
where everyone, when they were late
teenagers, they would serve a couple of
years of national service
which would include
all of the skills for
building the pyramids.
Okay, so back to the pyramids,
we know that they're now a project,
but they did not have the tools and
techniques of project management.
So then they feel the test for being
managed by project management.
and so this proves the projects can be
completed without project management.
The PIMBOC guide says that effective
project management helps individuals,
groups and public and private
organisations to meet business objectives,
to satisfy stakeholder expectations,
be more predictable, increase chances of
success, deliver the right products at the
right time, resolve problems and issues,
respond to risks in a timely manner,
optimise use of organisational resources,
identify, recover or terminate failing
projects, manage constraints, for example,
scope, quality, schedule, costs and
resources, balance the influence of
constraints on a project, example,
increase scope may increase cost or
schedule and manage change in a better
manner.
When you come to the examination,
you'll find there's 200 questions.
All of the questions are multiple choice
and you're choosing from four answers.
And you will find there could be a
question which will ask something like how
does project management help an
organisation.
And it will be a list of several from the
list which I've just read.
will be the correct answer.
The PIMBOC guide goes on to say that
poorly managed projects or the absence of
project management may result in missed
deadlines, cost overruns, per quality,
rework, uncontrolled expansion of the
project, loss of reputation for the
organisation, unsatisfied stakeholders,
and failure in achieving the objectives
for which the project was undertaken,
Again, there could be a question in the
examination for examples of how the
absence of project management can harm an
organisation and they'll be chosen from
that list.
The PINBock guide makes
an important point that projects
are a key way to create value
and benefits in organisations.
Yet strangely the definition
of a project and the
definition of project management
do not mention benefits.
See, if you're familiar with Prince 2,
this might seem a bit strange here.
With each person here, organisations are
called upon to do more or less.
And I'm sure you're probably in that
situation.
They have to become ever more efficient.
They need to reduce costs and delivery
times, but without reducing quality.
And that's why on the news
we see so much interest in
machine learning, artificial
intelligence and robots.
The robots can either be the type of
mechanical robots that build cars or they
could be the software
type robots which can enter
thousands of invoices in
10 seconds or something.
These are all examples of trying to do
more with less.
And the only way that they
can succeed is by ensuring
that projects are managed
using robust project management.
Otherwise, they will be a drain on the
resources instead of
adding to their effects.
And going forward, I can see more and more
organisations adapting
agile methods of delivery.
And you can see that the
PIMBOC guide 6 edition has
introduced a lot of
information on agile methods.
Now, there won't be a lot of us asked on
the examination.
It'll be quite a high level, but still
it's coming into the PIMBOC, and not only
that whenever you buy the PIMBOC guide,
or if you're a member of PMI, you can
download electronic version of the PIMBOC
guide free of charge it also comes with
the book on PMI Agile Methods and that
brings us to the end of the importance of
project management please remember to
learn the definition of project management
for the exam and also refresh your memory
on the list of advantages of project
management and the
disadvantages of not having project
management in case you get
an examination question that too.
The next lesson is 1.3
relationship between project,
programme, portfolio and
operations management.
Please read the corresponding chapter in
the PIMBOC guide before watching the video
so that you can have a good relationship
with this course.